<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ui on Bison Design</title>
    <link>http://bisondesign.net/tags/ui/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ui on Bison Design</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>All rights reserved - 2017</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://bisondesign.net/tags/ui/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A Metric for Simplicity</title>
      <link>http://bisondesign.net/post/metric-for-simplicity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://bisondesign.net/post/metric-for-simplicity/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-value-of-simplicity&#34;&gt;The value of simplicity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most complex requirement in software development is simplicity. In this post I
will describe a technique for measuring the simplicity of a UI design. This can be
used to choose the simplest design from a selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently ran a training exercise in problem solving with an audience of 50
top developers at a large corporation. Technology companies need to
innovate in order to stay ahead of the competition but innovation requires
problem solving.  But before we can solve problems we need to find them. For
example, I never knew that I absolutely &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to have a fingerprint reader on my
phone until my wife got one. Whoever discovered that we all need a fingerprint
reader was a genius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The true genious of this invention is that it is so simple; even a
toddler can learn to unlock a phone if the parents are crazy enough to
register his fingerprints on it. Simplification (represented by the meme &amp;ldquo;Less
if More&amp;rdquo;) is part of solution refinement, the often skipped last step in problem
solving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-meaning-of-simplicity&#34;&gt;The meaning of simplicity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simplicity has different manifestations in different domains. In mathematics it
is often referred to as elegance. An elegant solution is clear, concise, and
surprising. My favorite example is Cantor&amp;rsquo;s demonstration that the real numbers
are uncoutably infinite. Here he explains it to David Hilbert:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://bisondesign.net/images/Diagonal-Proof.png&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Cantor&amp;rsquo;s proof had been clunky, the result would have been just as
beneficial to mathematicians. A clunky proof woudn&amp;rsquo;t really matter as long as
it was still correct. Still, elegant proofs are a delight to behold, even on
repeated viewing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simplicity in software matters. Your product (whether it&amp;rsquo;s an app or a service)
is not an end in itself but a means to an end. In the UI complexity impedes the
end user from doing his task. In code complexity impedes maintainability. In
software design complexity impedes flexibility. A clunky UI, a clunky design
and a clunky implementation do matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simplicity in software design which closely resembles elegance in mathematics,
is the subject of a future blog post. Here we will stick with the user
experience and in particular simplicity in the UI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-model-for-the-interaction-of-a-human-with-the-ui&#34;&gt;A model for the interaction of a human with the UI&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A milestone in the field of usability in computer systems was the publication
of &amp;ldquo;The Psychology of Human-Computer Interaction&amp;rdquo; by Card, Moran, and Newell
(1983). The authors proposed a model of the &amp;ldquo;Human processor&amp;rdquo; citing ten
scientific principles of operation, like &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fitts&#39;s_law&#34; title=&#34;Fitts&#39;s law - Wikipedia&#34;&gt;Fitts&amp;rsquo;s law&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_law_of_practice&#34; title=&#34;Power Law of Practice - Wikipedia&#34;&gt;Power Law
of Practice&lt;/a&gt; based on empirical data.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://bisondesign.net/images/03-HumanProcessor_Card_Moran_Newell_1983.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Models are useful for analysis. The suitability of a model can be judged by its
predictive accuracy. Our model of human-computer interaction will be simpler
than the image above which comes from the book, but it will use some of the same
ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose automated analysis could be added to a UI design tool such as
&lt;a href=&#34;https://balsamiq.com/&#34;&gt;Balamiq Mockups&lt;/a&gt; to help assess the usability of a UI for performing
a specific task at the design stage. Given a task, the UI designer would click,
type and drag to complete the actions needed to complete the task using the
mock, imitating the future user. These would be recorded and analyzed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A UI can be designed to accomplish multiple tasks. For example, the same UI may
be used to create an account or change a password: two distinct tasks. In that
case both tasks would be considered in the analysis of the UI. These would not
be given equal weight however. The weight of a task to a given persona will be
proportional to its frequency. For example the number of times that task needs
to be accomplished in a typical year, month or week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being able to accomplish a task is not enough. That&amp;rsquo;s basic suitability
testing. Each interaction with and transition between UI components has a cost.
Clicking on an item that is a big target costs less than if it were small. The
distance the pointer has to move has a cost. Picking an item in a cluttered
menu has a higher cost than clean ones. The sum of the costs is &amp;ldquo;inefficiency&amp;rdquo;.
Our goal will be to minimize inefficiency over the task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simplicity can be measured by the amount of &amp;ldquo;ink&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;clutter&amp;rdquo; in the UI. Less
is more! In a good UI the quotient of task value, divided by simplicity and
efficiency is the metric by which I will judge the UI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sequence is not necessarily unique.  Sometimes the sequence is constrained,
as when a button is disabled until certain fields are filled in properly.  These
variation can be measured as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has gotten long enough.  In a future blog post I will discuss:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the model of human behavior while interacting with a UI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;measuring the cost of learning a UI by repeated performance of the same tasks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;metric limitations, given different users have different experience levels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use of deep learning to refine the model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] Card, Stuart K.; Moran, Thomas P.; Newell, Allen (1983). The Psychology of
Human–Computer Interaction. Hillsdale, NJ: L. Erlbaum Associates. ISBN
0898592437.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>