<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Bison Design</title>
    <link>http://bisondesign.net/post/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Bison Design</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>All rights reserved - 2017</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 20:21:11 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://bisondesign.net/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Fast Username Validation</title>
      <link>http://bisondesign.net/post/fast-username-validation/fast-username-validation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 20:21:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://bisondesign.net/post/fast-username-validation/fast-username-validation/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;success-leads-to-failure&#34;&gt;Success leads to failure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You run a site where customers create an account with a user name and password.
Your site is wildly successful and more customers flock to join. Soon all
the good user names are taken. With all your success the fundamental user
experience of creating an account begins to suck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? The first group of users naturally choose their first name. But there are
4.8 million &lt;em&gt;James&lt;/em&gt; in the United States and almost as many &lt;em&gt;Johns&lt;/em&gt;. The
&lt;a href=&#34;http://names.mongabay.com/male_names.htm&#34;&gt;twenty most common male names&lt;/a&gt;
account for 32 percent of the male population. There are about 4 million
&lt;em&gt;Marys&lt;/em&gt; and 1.6 million &lt;em&gt;Patricias&lt;/em&gt;. Incredibly prospective customers are told,
&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sorry, username &amp;lsquo;Maurice&amp;rsquo; is already taken&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First initial and last name will go a lot further. However, thanks to human
psychology, we again run out of steam sooner than you expect. At my company,
there were three John Lloyds. Some first names just sound better with a
lastname like John and Lloyd. As a parent of five I can attest to thinking a
lot about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- img src=&#34;https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/baby_names.png&#34;/ --&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;username-validation-requirements&#34;&gt;Username validation requirements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time you reach 50,000 users (congratulations, by the way) your sucky UI
will require the user to make repeated attempts to find a name that is not
taken. Some frustrated non-customers are giving up; now you need to fix this
problem quickly. For the ideal user experience your account creation UI needs
to be simple and responsive.  It should have these properties:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A visual queue that the name being typed is not yet taken&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Less than 0.5s latency when checking if a given name is taken&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visual queue could be a greyed out &amp;ldquo;Submit&amp;rdquo; button whenever the name is
already taken. It could also be a pink background in the user name text input
box. With these improvements, your customers will once again be able to choose
a name easily without the heartbreak of repeated rejections. The low latency
is needed for the impression of a responive UI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
   &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://bisondesign.net/images/NewAccountDialogEmpty.png&#34;/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://bisondesign.net/images/NewAccountMissingPassword.png&#34;/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://bisondesign.net/images/NewAccountReadyToSubmit.png&#34;/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three images above show how a simple dialog can provide feedback for a
taken username, a weak password, and a non-matching confirmation. In all
cases the background is pink when there is a problem.  The submit button
is enabled only once all three problems are eliminated.  Doing all three
checks on the client side leads to a repsonsive and simple user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;knowing-what-you-don-t-know-probabilistic-data-structures&#34;&gt;Knowing what you don&amp;rsquo;t know: probabilistic data structures&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This type of behavior should be done in JavaScript on the browser.
Unfortunately, you can&amp;rsquo;t just download a long list of taken names. Even a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trie&#34;&gt;trie&lt;/a&gt; of names is too big. A trie can
compress common prefixes but the number of nodes is still proportional to the
number of distinct names in the trie. The sheer number of names appears to make
a client side solution impossible. Unless of course you are willing to trade
off certainty for size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter a probabilistic data structure called a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloom_filter&#34;&gt;Bloom
Filter&lt;/a&gt;. Probabilistic algorithms
behave like normal algorithms but have a theoretical chance of being wrong. The
trade off is that they act faster or require less memory to produce the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Bloom Filter is a probabilistic (unreliable) set. Unlike a trie, a Bloom
Filter can compress both the letters and the number of words in a collection to
an in-memory bit vector. You can&amp;rsquo;t always trust that a true result from testing
set membership is correct, but a simple formula gives staticstical limits on
the number of false positives. Here is how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose the bit vector has size M, where M is very large. To add user name S to
the filter, compute k hash values ${h_0(S), h_1(S), &amp;hellip;, h_k(S)}$ and set
those bits to 1. The k hash functions should be &lt;em&gt;independent&lt;/em&gt;. The numbers M
and k are selected based on the expected number of names. Checking for the presence
of a name involves calculating the same set of bits and testing it they are set.
If even one of them is not set, then the name could not be present in the fitler.
If, however, they are all set, the name is only likely to be present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The space advantage in a Bloom Filter comes from the compactness from the data
structure. A Bloom filter with 1% error and an optimal value of k, requires
only about 9.6 bits (1.2 bytes) per element — regardless of the size of the
elements.  So a site with 50,000 user names would require 64K bytes for a filter.
That&amp;rsquo;s the size of a small (400x600) gif image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A word of caution. The theoretical percent error assumes the hash functions are
mutually independent.  It is not that easy to get a family of independent hash
functions, but based on my research the error is not too far off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;edge-cases-and-recommendations&#34;&gt;Edge cases and Recommendations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a delay between the time that the bloom filter is calculated on the
server and when it is used on the client.  Suppose for the sake of argument that
your site has 50,000 names and adds 600 more users every day.  The bloom filter
may be recalculated 6 times a day and republished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a new user happens to pick one if these 100 new user names before they are
added they &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; still get a false negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you do when a false negative happens? The simplest solution is to blame
latency. The user does not know that we are calculating taken names locally
using a Bloom Filter. The UI could optimistically send the names being typed
(after a 0.5 second pause) on to the server to validate.  If the latency to
your server is small, the additional check will only take an extra second.  If
the name is indeed still not taken, the &amp;ldquo;Submit&amp;rdquo; button can be enabled.  If
it happended to be among the 100 newly added names, that fact is sent to the
client which adds the name to a stoplist of known taken names.  The stoplist
can be uploaded along with the Bloom Filter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you start out your web site all you really need is a stoplist to get the
same user experience. One thousand 20 letter user names is only 20K
un-compressed. Design your UX to scale up to 50 or 100 times as many users and
change the test to use a bloom filter when the download size of the stoplist
get&amp;rsquo;s too big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;limitations-and-conclusion&#34;&gt;Limitations and Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook has over 1.8 billion active users. A Bloom Filter solution will not
scale to Facebook proportions. Google has the same &amp;lsquo;problem&amp;rsquo;. In these cases
validation happens on the server and the server suggests a number of untaken
names to the user following certain patterns. Can you think of a way in which
the giant could improve on this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck and I hope you enjoyed my first technical blog post. In the future
I will share some code for making fast username validation happen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to Bison Design</title>
      <link>http://bisondesign.net/post/bisondesign/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 15:31:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://bisondesign.net/post/bisondesign/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the Bison Design blog!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crafting software is an art. My training in mathematics and decades of
experience &lt;/br&gt;developing enterprise software gave me a unique perspective to
appreciate its beauty. The search for simplicity influenced my designs and
this is the subject of my blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope the excitement I feel upon finding that simplicity comes across in a way
that is both educational and entertaining. If you find these pages interesting
please share your insights in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>